<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The friendly conference: or, An hue and cry after the Popes Holiness Discovering the corrupt doctrines of the church, and abominable practises of the court and clergy of Rome, to raise themselves to their present pomp and grandeur. With the several prodigious births of the whore of Babilon: and how she has prefer'd all her children. In a familiar dialogue between Theophilius a Protestant, and Juliano lately turn'd Papist.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215515</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827369</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827369</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31787</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40487)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31787)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1908:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The friendly conference: or, An hue and cry after the Popes Holiness Discovering the corrupt doctrines of the church, and abominable practises of the court and clergy of Rome, to raise themselves to their present pomp and grandeur. With the several prodigious births of the whore of Babilon: and how she has prefer'd all her children. In a familiar dialogue between Theophilius a Protestant, and Juliano lately turn'd Papist.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M.B.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year, 1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Popes --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31787:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31787:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Friendly Conference OR, AN HUE and CRY After the POPES HOLINESS. Diſcovering the corrupt Doctrines of the CHURCH, and abominable Practiſes of the COURT and CLERGY of ROME, To raiſe themſelves to their preſent Pomp and Grandeur.</p>
            <p>With the ſeveral Prodigious Births of the Whore of Babilon: And how ſhe has prefer'd all her Children.</p>
            <p>In a familiar Dialogue between <hi>Theophilus</hi> a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and <hi>Juliano</hi> lately turn'd <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>M. B.</hi> in the Year, 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:31787:2"/>
            <head>A HUE AND CRY After the Popes Holineſs, &amp;c.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juliano.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>YOur Servant Neighbour <hi>Theophilus.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophilus.</speaker>
               <p>I am heartily glad to ſee you <hi>Juliano,</hi> the rather for that I was lately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed you were dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juliano.</speaker>
               <p>How? dead! have people talkt me into a Ghoſt? I'le e'en run to the Prerogative and enter a Caveat my ſelf, leaſt ſome Kn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve or other ſhould take Adminiſtration of my Eſtate. Dead! I proteſt I know no buſineſs I ſhall have in the other World this fifty years: There's nothing in Nature I hate ſo much as dying this cold weather, for truly I conceive a Tomb, though made of Marble, and placed in the Chancel, but a damp untoward Lodging; beſides it yields no good company, for the men loſe their Sences before they come thither; and as ſoon as the women have been there a while, they all grow flat-nos'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theoph.</speaker>
               <p>I perceive you mind dying but little; but if you fear catching cold in your Grave, you were beſt charge your Executor to bury you Legally in Flannel: however I doubt you may have more reaſon to aprehend burning torments, than Cold, for I hear you are dead Spiritually: I mean, <hi>Twice dead and pluckt up by the roots,</hi> as the Apoſtle Phraſes it: That you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:31787:2"/> have forfeited your Diſcretion, caſt your Reaſon over-board, and abandon'd your Religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juliano.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I hate diſſembling, and muſt own my ſelf a <hi>Roman-Catholick.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theoph.</speaker>
               <p>Can you hate Diſſemulation, and yet own at the ſame time a Religion that is made up of nothing but Frauds, Cheats, and Deluſions: That very Title <hi>Roman Catholique,</hi> is a Falicy, or at beſt an Abſurdity in Terminis; for ſince the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and proper ſignification of the Word <hi>Catholique</hi> is no more then general or univerſal: to joyn <hi>Rome</hi> to it, is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignificant Bull, and as pure non-ſence, as to ſay a particular, Univerſal, or a general Individual.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juliano.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſhall not quarrel with you about words; I am a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> that <hi>Mother Church</hi> where true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion has flouriſht ever ſince it was firſt planted there, by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in an uninterupted Succeſſion: that Church to which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our has given Priviledge to be the infallible Judge of all Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and promiſed, <hi>the gates of Hell ſhall never prevail againſt it</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theoph.</speaker>
               <p>Alas Sir! you boaſt of the Casket when the Jewels are gone; The <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> ſailing under the merry gale of Earthly pomp and proſperity, has long ſince diſcharged her ſelf of that rich Laden ſhe was fraught with, when ſhe Traded for Souls under the Fathers of the Primitive Ages, there having ſince been ſuch a ſucceſſion of Imperious great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in that Chair, that <hi>Rome</hi> is more like the proud triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Chappel of Antichriſt, than the poor militant Church of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juliano.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Primary ever the Apoſtles and Spirit of infabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity was delivered to <hi>Peter,</hi> and thence conveyed down in his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo that there could be no ſuch Apoſtacy as you pretend.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theoph.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe parivolous pretences are eaſily confuted; but not to enter into a tedious Diſcourſe, I ſhall only ask you this ſerious Queſtion, ſince you can caſt your eyes upon no ſtory where the villary of Popes is not largely diſcovered, how can you conceit that the pure Spirit of God ſhould endow with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31787:3"/> infalibility of judgement, Monſters ſo viſibly debauch'd? or how can you believe the Holy Ghoſt, which under the Law forbad all impurity, though in outward Ceremony ſhould now under the brighter light of the Goſpel ſuffer himſelf to be poured out of one unclean veſſel, into another, beginning again with a Conjurer, where he left off with a <hi>Sodomite?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juliano.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I cannot believe any Popes were ever guilty of ſuch Crimes, or if they were, theſe are ſtill perſonal Infirmities.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theoph.</speaker>
               <p>But moſt groſs ones in thoſe that blaſphemouſly ſtile themſelves <hi>Their Holineſſes,</hi> and impudently boaſt to the world that they cannot err, nor can deny the truth of their impieties, as to matter of fact without proclaiming your own ignorance in Hiſtory.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juliano.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truly Sir, you know I am but a Lay-man, and do not pretend too much Reading.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theoph.</speaker>
               <p>The fitter to imbrace a Religion, whoſe chiefeſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port is ignorance: But for your information, I care not if I draw a ſhort Hiſtorical Scheme of your Romiſh Church, that you may ſee by what means and degrees it firſt intruded to that Grandeur, with the gawdy Luſtre whereof your eyes have been ſo far dazled, as to chuſe a Cloud for Juno, change a Diamond for a Briſtol-ſtone, and forſake the true Spouſe of Chriſt, to wantonize in the embraces of a painted Harlot.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juliano.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am ſatisfied with my choice, yet care not if I give you the hearing, ſince you will needs take upon you as a Doctor.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theoph.</speaker>
               <p>Thus then, after the piety of ſome primitive Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> augmented by the flame of that Imperial City had purchaſed them reputation, ſo that they got firſt to be Arch-Biſhops, then Patriarchs, and at laſt to the Papal Title (A name 'tis thought derived <hi>Quaſie pater Patriarcharum</hi>) which for Brevity was written <hi>Papa.</hi>) They ſoon began to change their piety for promotion, and takeing the advantage of new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindled zeal, whereby they led Princes and people at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; they had the opportunity to carve themſelves almoſt what power or Riches they liſt. But as policy can ſeldome tread long in that narrow path that guides to Heaven, ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31787:3"/> at laſt it led them into a World of Impieties, by encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under pretence of Religion, upon higher Juriſdiction and power, than could belong to ſubjects, which they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour'd as the Donations of Princes, who had indeed no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Titles to their Crowns than Uſurpation on the weakneſſe of the former poſſeſſors: And were therefore glad of the Popes protection, becauſe people out of Ignorance eſteemed thoſe moſt juſt that were moſt favour'd by the Clergy. Thus a bargain was often driven for mutual aſſiſtance between U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers and the Pope, who in his approbations diligently laid up their petitions, and his grants to remain as preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents whereby to guide to poſterity. The Cloud of Ignor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance then covering the World, was a great help to keep their Juggling undiſcovered; that little learning extant, was wholly included in Monaſtick Cells; who took the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to make moſt Books ſpeak in their favour: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only a few Manuſcripts might eaſily be effected. Beſides the Clergy were kept unmarried on purpoſe, that being free from all other obligations, they might ſolely intend the promoting their own Intereſt, (which they called the power and Immunities of the Church) So that in time by the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of good, and neceſſity of wicked and Illegitimate prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they freed their whole ſociety from the temporal Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction: And now having purchaſed Eaſe, Honour, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity; ſuch as were Poor, Guilty, or Ambitious, Liſted themſelves of their fellowſhip, and being for the moſt part of the beſt Abilities, ſoon learned the skill ſo to work on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of dying people affrighted with their ſins, that the Church was left Heir of the beſt part of Chriſtendome. Nor did they only make uſe of the profitable errors left them by their fore-fathers, but brought in new ones of their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triveing, guilding them with the ſplendid Tytles of things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and of Religious uſe: Thus Images came to be Idoliz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Cognizance of the Croſs made a Tutelary God, looking no higher in their Extremities, and the bleſſed Saints ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized with the worſhip given to them, and their Reliques.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31787:4"/> Thus a fire is kindled in purgatory, only to maintain that in the Popes Kitchin, confeſſion is deviſed as a pick-lock to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover each mans ſecrets, pardons for all paſt ſins, and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences for never ſo many to come, are publiquely Expoſed, and in brief all Religion almoſt made ſubſervient to their Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies &amp; curſed Avarice; whilſt the Monks and all ſorts of Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are daily promoted and armed with Immenſe priviledges, as a ſtrong and faithful Militia in all Countries for the Sea of Rome, yet fed and paid by the reſpective Princes, that tame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffer themſelves to be enſlaved by Popiſh Tyranny. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude moſt of the things in diſpute, which you would Impoſe on our Church concern, either profit or honour; and were brought in by the ſubtile Preiſts long ſince the primitive times, taking advantage from the Ignorance of preceeding Ages, nor can ſuch Papiſts as are wiſe converſant in Hiſtory, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the preſent practice of the Court of Rome, but be ſouly ſuſpected of Atheiſme, becauſe conſcience can never be perſwaded againſt a convinceing experience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juliano.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sure you have rail'd your ſelf out of breath by this time againſt the Pope, but I cannot now ſtand to anſwer your Invective ſtory particularly, haveing ſome occaſions that oblige me to take my leave.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theoph.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall freely diſmiſs you, only deſire you would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you go, favour me with ſome brief Relation, how you came to be thus ſeduced, winnow and ſift your heart, to find out what threw you into this Abiſs. He that falls into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by breaking through the Ice, muſt riſe where he fell, or he is loſt beyond recovery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juliano.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truly Sir, I came to embrace the Catholique Religion; as it were by accident, being about two Months ago, at my Cozen Eſquire <hi>Preiſtridden's</hi> after Dinner being very merry; Topeing off three or four dozen Bottles of wine, with two ſtrange Gentlemen, that happen'd to be there, one of them began by degrees to feel my pulſe as to Religion, and did applaud the Romiſh Church as the onely certain true eaſie and orthodox way, and ſo far decry the proteſtant, that I who then had more mind to ſleep than diſpute, knew not ſcarce
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31787:4"/> what to anſwer; and at laſt the whole Company plying me ſo hard at once with ſtrong Arguments, and full Glaſſes, that I ſeemingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented; whereupon next day the two Gentlemen (who as I may tell you under the Roſe were a couple of reveren'd Fathers of t<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſociety of Jeſus) came to my houſe, and there continued till they had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated my Converſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theoph.</speaker>
               <p>A moſt excellent method. Theſe are the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> who compaſs Land and Sea for a proſelite, and barbarouſly cauſed more than a 100000 ſilly <hi>Americans</hi> to be murthered, to the diſgrace of Chriſtianity, I cannot but adm<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re ſo many of our Engliſh Gentry (in other things very Judicious) ſhould ſuffer themſelves to be rookt, oppreſt, enſlaved, and often undone by theſe <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Locuſts. I knew a young Gentleman of 2000l. a year, married not above three years ago into a Catholike family, who by their art ſeduced him to their Religion; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he was continually haunted with ſuch Shoals of theſe Roman Horſleaches, that preying continually on his means, they ſoon brought his eſtate into a Conſumption, and his wife dying, wheadled him to beſtow the remainder on a Colledge of theirs, &amp; Imure himſelf for the wretched remainder of his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife in a Monaſtery: thus they bought their Pallace at <hi>Dulevort,</hi> with the vaſt <hi>portion</hi> of a <hi>ghoſt-led Maid,</hi> who was forced after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to Live afflictedly upon their ſorry Alms, and repent of her miſtaken Charity. Thus their Abbey of Lanſpring, they ſubtlely recovered from the <hi>Lutherans;</hi> ſo they fool'd a doat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing old Abbot with falſe Alarms out of England, till he Inveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them in their Colledge at <hi>Doway,</hi> &amp; purchaſed their ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Houſe at <hi>Paris,</hi> by a trick no leſs Impious and fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. In brief, Treaſon, Rebellion, Fraud, Deceit, and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention <hi>have bin</hi> their continual ſtudy, ſince <hi>Loyola</hi> hatcht them into the world, concerning which I ſhall only tell you one ſtory; and then refer you to your occaſions. Once upon a time, (for ſo all tales uſe to beg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n) <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome</hi> was with-child, and ſhe brought forth her eldeſt Son. The Benedictine Monk, to him as Heir ſhe gave her Lands, ſhe remain'd free a while, but at laſt ſhe was with child again, and brought into the Light
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31787:5"/> Twins. The <hi>Dominican</hi> and the <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Fryer: to the firſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already beſtowed her Lands. ſhe gave certain Houſes &amp; Moneys by way of penſion: to the other (having now nothing elſe leſt) The Wallet, and ſet him out of doors a begging: ſhe ſtood clear again for a conſiderable time, till at laſt ſhe was once more Mountain-big, ſhe long'd, ſhe groan'd, ſhe drew her breath ſhort, and made ſtore of out-landiſh faces, but in Concluſion gave the World a Luſty Boy, who was no ſooner born, out he utter'd from natures backdoor, the Midwives Lapful, which was interpreted an omen of future good Luck. This was the fiery <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> and his Mother having given away Lands, Houſes, Wallet and all, took him up gave him a ſmart clap on the right Buttock, and ſaid, My Darling, ſhift for thy ſelf, and ſo he has done ever ſince moſt accurately, to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of all places where he comes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juliano.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will be in Debt to you for this ſtory till our next meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: In the Interim, conſider your condition, and remember, that out of the Church there is no Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theoph.</speaker>
               <p>I do conſider my own condition and pitty yours; remembring the puniſhment attending them who turn their backs on ſacred truths, they have once profeſſed, and make void the Law of God by their vain Traditions.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a balance containing the bible in one pan and objects representing eccesiastical tradition in the other</figDesc>
                  <p>The Bibl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e con<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>g the word of God.</p>
                  <p>The D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cr<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g M<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:31787:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
